Mss.Ms.Coll.113
American Philosophical Society
Herbert Friedman Papers
1940-2000
Mss.Ms.Coll.113
American Philosophical Society
31.0 Linear feet
31 linear feet.
Friedman, Herbert, 1916-2000
Box 1-60
Biographical/Historical note
Herbert Friedman was born in Brooklyn, New York and graduated from Brooklyn College in 1936 (BS) and from Johns Hopkins (Phd, Physics). He joined the Naval Research Laboratory in 1940, and until about 1950 maintained an active research program in applied x-ray spectroscopy. In 1949 he conducted his first of many space experiments comprising a set of x-ray and ultraviolet sensitive geiger counters to observe the Sun.
Friedman is recognized as one of the pioneers of space science for his contributions to solar physics, upper atmospheric physics and x-ray astronomy. He was also recognized as one of the great statesman of the discipline having been a member of the President's Science Advisory Committee, the General Advisory Committee to the Atomic Energy Commission, the Space Science Board of the National Academy of Sciences, the Governing Board of the National Academy of Sciences. His awards include the Eddington Medal of the Royal Astronomical Society, the National Medal of Science, the William Bowie Medal of the American Geophysical Society, the Henry Norris Russell Award of the American Astronomical Society and the Wolf Foundation Prize in Physics. He was elected a member of the National Academy of Science in 1960. He retired from the Naval Research Laboratory in 1980 but continued an association with the Laboratory as a consultant and as Chief Scientist, emeritus.
Conditions Governing Access note
Access to Series XIV - Restricted Nominations and Personnel Files has been restricted.
Atmospheric astronomy; Solar physics; X-ray astronomy
- Series I. Correspondence, 2.5 linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I consists of Dr. Friedman’s personal correspondence. It is organized alphabetically with the bulk placed in miscellaneous files. The largest file consists of correspondence with Edward O. Hulburt, Dr. Friedman’s mentor and namesake of the Edward O. Hulburt Center for Space Research at the Navy Research Laboratory.
  - A- Misc., 1968-1992; 35.0 items (Box 1)
  - 1965, 2.0 items; 2 items; American Men of Science. (Box 1)
  - 1975-1976, 5.0 items; American Scientist. (Box 1)
  - B - Misc., 1964-1988; 83.0 items (Box 1)
  - 1932; 1989, 2.0 items; 2 items; Bearn, Alexander G., 1923-2009 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1964, 5.0 items; Benesch, William (Box 1)
  - Birthday Correspondence, 1976; 1996; 15.0 items; 17 items (Box 1)
    Correspondence received on the occasion of Dr. Friedman's 60th and 80th birthdays.
  - 1967-1968, 12.0 items; Blake, Richard (Box 1)
  - 1991-1996; undated, 29.0 items; 27 items; Blifford, Irving
    Includes Ground Station Manuals that were enclosed with correspondence.
  - 1965-1971, 7.0 items; Bowyer, Stuart C. (Box 1)
  - 1964-1979, 13.0 items; British Broadcasting Corporation. (Box 1)
  - 1998, 1.0 item; Buckley, B. W. (Box 1)
  - C - Misc., 1959-1992; 54.0 items (Box 1)
  - 1975, 1.0 item; Cannon, Howard (Box 1)
  - 1970, 5.0 items; Carriger, David, Jr. (Box 1)
  - 1963-1965, 2.0 items; 2 items; Cavanaugh, Robert (Box 1)
  - 1970, 2.0 items; 2 items; Clemens, Cyril, 1902- (Box 1)
    Two letters regarding Dr. Friedman's election as a Knight of Mark Twain.
  - 1973-1978, 6.0 items; Committee of Concerned Scientists. (Box 1)
  - 1979, 4.0 items; Córdova, France A. (Box 1)
  - Crackpot Letters, 1954; 1960; undated; 9.0 items; 9 items (Box 1)
  - 1972, 5.0 items; Cunkle, Wendy (Box 1)
  - D - Misc, 1958-1981; 36.0 items (Box 1)
  - 1974-1978, 12.0 items; Davidsen, Arthur Falnes. (Box 1)
  - 1975-1976, 10.0 items; Dean, Colin (Box 1)
  - 1992, 6.0 items; Donahue, Thomas M. (Box 1)
  - E - Misc., 1984-2000; 24.0 items (Box 1)
  - 1988, 4.0 items; Edelson, Burton I. (Box 1)
  - Encyclopedia of Physical Science and Technology, 1998-1999; 12.0 items; 11 items (Box 1)
    Includes 1998 Topical Outline for 3rd edition of the Encyclopedia.
  - Encyclopedia of Space Science and Technology, 1998; 2.0 items; 2 items (Box 1)
  - F - Misc., 1962-1989; 57.0 items (Box 1)
  - 1957-1961, 4.0 items; Fierst, Herbert A. (Box 1)
  - 1973, 2.0 items; Fisher, Philip (Box 1)
  - G -Misc., 1961-1997; 59.0 items (Box 2)
  - 1961, 2.0 items; General Electric Company (Box 2)
  - 1966-1978, 11.0 items; 2 items; Giaccone, Riccardo (Box 2)
  - 1982, 1.0 item; 1 item; Gibson, R. E. (Box 2)
  - 1976, 6.0 items; Gillmor, C. Stewart, 1938- (Box 2)
  - 1981-1982, 4.0 items; Gingerich, Owen (Box 2)
  - 1976, 4.0 items; Gold, Thomas (Box 2)
  - 1979-1980, 6.0 items; Goldberg, David (Box 2)
  - 1963-1976, 14.0 items; Goldberg, Leo (Box 2)
  - 1989, 2.0 items; 2 items; Golden, William T., 1909-2007 (Box 2)
  - H - Misc., 1962-2000; 71.0 items (Box 2)
  - 1986, 2.0 items; Heckert, Richard Edwin, 1924-2010 (Box 2)
  - 1980, 6.0 items; Hirsch, Richard (Box 2)
  - 1959-1981, 31.0 items; 31 items; Hulbert, Edward (Box 2)
  - 1993-1994, 2.0 items; Hulst, H. C. van de (Hendrik Christoffel), 1918- (Box 2)
  - I - Misc., 1961-1996; 16.0 items (Box 2)
  - Il Nuovo Cimento, 1987; 1.0 item; 3 items (Box 2)
  - Institute of Physics Publishing, 1999; 2.0 items; 2 items (Box 2)
  - J - Misc., 1964-1993; 27.0 items (Box 2)
  - 1977, 2.0 items; 2 items; Jager, C. de (Cornelis), 1921- (Box 2)
  - John Wiley & Sons, Inc., 1964; 3.0 items (Box 2)
  - 1989, 2.0 items; 2 items; Johnson, Frank (Box 2)
  - K - Misc., 1957-1998; 36.0 items (Box 2)
  - 1967-1974, 4.0 items; Kaplan, Joseph A., 1902-1991 (Box 2)
  - 1990, 4.0 items; Kellerman, Ken (Box 2)
  - 1987, 2.0 items; 2 items; Kippenhahn, Rudolf, 1926- (Box 2)
  - Kitt Peak National Observatory, 1961; 1.0 item; 1 item (Box 2)
  - 1982, 1.0 item; 1 item; Koroff, Serge A. (Box 2)
  - L - Misc., 1961-1993; 30.0 items (Box 2)
  - 1990, 2.0 items; Levy, Eugene H. (Eugene Howard), 1944- (Box 2)
  - 1995-1996, 3.0 items; 3 items; Lockhart, Luther B. (Box 2)
  - M - Misc., 1961-1997; 62.0 items (Box 2)
  - 1967-1986, 66.0 items; Mandelshtam, S. L. (Box 2)
  - Martin-Marietta Corporation, 1969-1971; 6.0 items
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1978-1979; 5.0 items (Box 2)
  - 1997, 3.0 items; Michels, Donald J. (Box 2)
  - 1991, 3.0 items; Milne, John (Box 2)
  - 1961, 2.0 items; Moe, Henry Allen, 1894-1975
  - N - Misc., 1960-1980; 61.0 items (Box 3)
  - 1978-1983, 6.0 items; Naranan, Sundaresan (Box 3)
  - 1997; undated, 3.0 items; National Radio Astronomy Observatory (U.S.). (Box 3)
  - 1962-1964, 6.0 items; 6 items; National Register of Scientific and Technical Personnel. (Box 3)
  - 1988-1994, 6.0 items; 5 items; Ne'eman, Yuval (Box 3)
  - 1967, 2.0 items; 2 items; New York Academy of Sciences. (Box 3)
  - 1979, 1.0 item; Nicolet, Marcel (Box 3)
  - 1973, 1.0 item; 1 item; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913- (Box 3)
    This letter from President Nixon to Dr. Friedman accepts Dr. Friedman's resignation as Chief Scientist of the E. O. Hulburt Center for Space Research under the U.S. Naval Research Laboratory. It also informs Dr. Friedman that President Nixon plans to reorganize and thus disband the President's Science Advisory Committee.
  - O - Misc., 1962-1988; 10.0 items (Box 3)
  - 1969, 3.0 items; 3 items; O’Brien, Brian J., 1934- (Box 3)
  - 1988-1992; undated, 10.0 items; 10 items; Oda, Minoru, 1923- (Box 3)
  - 1964, 4.0 items; 4 items; Odishaw, Hugh (Box 3)
  - 1994-1995, 3.0 items; Oertel, Goetz (Box 3)
  - 1975; undated, 3.0 items; 3 items; O'Malley, Louise (Box 3)
  - 1990, 3.0 items; Osheroff, Douglas D. (Box 3)
  - 1964-1968, 4.0 items; Oster, Ludwig (Box 3)
  - 1971, 5.0 items; Owen, Thomas B. (Box 3)
  - P - Misc., 1961-2000; 24.0 items (Box 3)
  - Pacific Missile Range, 1962; 3.0 items (Box 3)
  - 1969, 2.0 items; Paolini, Frank (Box 3)
  - 1976, 2.0 items; Parker, E. N. (Eugene Newman), 1927- (Box 3)
  - 1978, 2.0 items; Pasachoff, Jay M. (Box 3)
  - Pawsey, J. L., 1960-1961; 3.0 items (Box 3)
  - 1967, 2.0 items; Peebles, P. J. E. (Phillip James Edwin) (Box 3)
  - 1978, 3.0 items; Penzias, Arno A. (Box 3)
  - 1978, 3.0 items; Perrenod, Stephen Charles (Box 3)
  - 1966-1978, 9.0 items; Peterson, Laurence E., 1931- (Box 3)
  - Physics Today, 1966; 3.0 items (Box 3)
  - 1976, 6.0 items; Piana, Anna (Box 3)
  - 1970, 1.0 item; Pesharoty, P. R. (Box 3)
  - 1974, 2.0 items; Pitts, Fred (Box 3)
  - 1969, 5.0 items; Platovsky, Kyra (Box 3)
  - Popular Science, 1971; 2.0 items (Box 3)
  - 1966, 2.0 items; Pounds, K. (Ken) (Box 1)
  - 1976-1977, 9.0 items; Prasad, Balram (Box 3)
  - 1972, 2.0 items; Pratt, R. H. (Box 3)
  - President's Committee on the National Medal of Science, Bulk, 1972-1974; 1972-1990; 10.0 items (Box 3)
  - 1970, 3.0 items; Press, Frank (Box 3)
  - 1976, 3.0 items; Purcell, Dewitt (Box 3)
  - R - Misc., 1959-1999; 22.0 items (Box 4)
  - Radioastron Mission, 1989-1990; 6.0 items (Box 4)
  - 1976-1977, 3.0 items; Rajsky, Vladimir (Box 4)
  - 1963-1964, 2.0 items; Ratcliffe, J. A. (John Ashworth) (Box 4)
  - Reader's Digest, 1965; 4.0 items (Box 4)
  - 1966, 3.0 items; Reines, Frederick, 1918-1998 (Box 4)
  - Retirement Correspondence, 1980; 23.0 items (Box 4)
  - 1982, 2.0 items; Roalstad, D. A. (Box 4)
  - 1982, 1.0 item; Roberts, Elliot B. (Box 4)
  - 1965, 2.0 items; Roberts, Walter O., 1915- (Box 4)
  - Rockefeller Public Service Awards Program, 1967-1974; 25.0 items (Box 4)
  - 1962, 3.0 items; Rollins College (Winter Park, Fla.). (Box 4)
  - 1975, 3.0 items; Rosenblum, A., 1943- (Box 4)
  - Rossi, Bruno Benedetto, 1905-, 1980; 2.0 items (Box 4)
    Rossi, Bruno Benedetto, 1905- -- Correspondence
  - 1980, 2.0 items; Ruzicka, Emil (Box 4)
  - S - Misc., 1961-1994; 65.0 items (Box 4)
  - 1981-1989, 8.0 items; Sadeh, Dror (Box 4)
  - 1976, 1.0 item; Sagan, Carl, 1934-1996 (Box 4)
  - 1968, 3.0 items; Sahade, Jorge (Box 4)
  - 1970, 2.0 items; Sandage, Allan (Box 4)
  - 1978-1979, 7.0 items; Sapp, Earle (Box 4)
  - 1967-1968, 2.0 items; Sarabhai, Vikram A., 1919-1971 (Box 4)
  - 1971-1979, 4.0 items; Schnopper, Herbert (Box 4)
  - 1977, 2.0 items; Schulman, James H. (Box 4)
  - Schwartz, Anthony M., 1972; 4.0 items (Box 4)
    Schwartz, Anthony M. (Anthony Max), 1908- -- Correspondence
  - Science (Magazine), 1963; 3.0 items (Box 4)
  - Science Service, 1960; 2.0 items (Box 4)
  - Scientific American, 1963-1964; 14.0 items (Box 4)
  - 1978, 3.0 items; Sehra, P. S. (Box 4)
  - 1988-2001, 7.0 items; Seitz, Frederick, 1911-2008 (Box 4)
  - 1974-1990, 12.0 items; Shapiro, Maurice (Box 4)
  - 1976, 2.0 items; Shapshak, Paul (Box 4)
  - 1969-1977, 6.0 items; Shklovskii, I. S. (Box 4)
  - 1983, 4.0 items; Shoemaker, E. M. (Eugene Merle), 1928-1997 (Box 4)
  - 1967, 2.0 items; Shor, Franc (Box 4)
  - 1993, 7.0 items; Simpson, John (Box 4)
  - Sky and Telescope, 1963-1964; 5.0 items (Box 4)
  - 1990-1991, 3.0 items; Societe astronomique de France. (Box 4)
  - Space Publications, Inc., 1967; 3.0 items (Box 4)
  - 1964, 2.0 items; Spielberg, Nathan (Box 4)
  - 1966, 1.0 item; Spitz, Armand (Box 4)
  - 1966-1974, 10.0 items; Spitzer, Lyman, 1914-1997 (Box 4)
  - 1966, 2.0 items; Stein, Wayne (Box 4)
  - 1977, 2.0 items; Strand, K. Aage (Kaj Aage), 1907- (Box 4)
  - 1968, 3.0 items; Strasser, Joel (Box 4)
  - 1967, 3.0 items; Sturrock, Peter A. (Peter Andrew) (Box 4)
  - 1963-1978, 9.0 items; Sullivan, Walter (Box 4)
  - 1979, 2.0 items; Summerfield, Martin (Box 4)
  - 1971, 3.0 items; Suomi, Verner (Box 4)
  - 1977, 2.0 items; Svestka, Zidenek (Box 4)
  - 1960-1961, 2.0 items; Swarup, G. (Box 4)
  - 1962-1966, 7.0 items; Swings, P., (Polydore), 1906-1983 (Box 4)
  - T - Misc., 1961-2000; 29.0 items (Box 5)
  - 1976-1980, 7.0 items; Tananbaum, Harvey D. (Box 5)
  - 1975, 7.0 items; Tauber, Gerard (Box 5)
  - 1967, 1.0 item; Tawes, J. Millard, 1894-1979 (Box 5)
  - 1970, 1.0 item; Teague, Olin E., 1910-1981 (Box 5)
  - Ted, Undated; 3.0 items (Box 5)
  - Tel-Aviv Observatory, 1968-1971; 16.0 items (Box 5)
  - 1964-1965, 9.0 items; Thomas, Shirley (Box 5)
  - 1977-1993, 4.0 items; Thorne, Kip S. (Box 5)
  - 1962, 3.0 items; Thornton, Edward
  - TWA, 1991; 3.0 items (Box 5)
  - 1976, 3.0 items; Turner, Martin (Box 5)
  - 1975, 2.0 items; Tuve, Merle Antony, 1901-1982 (Box 5)
  - U - Misc., 1963-1992; 18.0 items (Box 5)
  - UCLA, 1962 (Box 5)
  - USN Medical School (B.W. Hogan), 1951; 1.0 item (Box 5)
  - University of Chicago, 1962; 3.0 items (Box 5)
  - University of Michigan, 1978; 2.0 items (Box 5)
  - University of Tubingen, 1975; 6.0 items (Box 5)
  - University of Wyoming, 1972-1973; 9.0 items (Box 5)
  - V - Misc., 1961-1983; 11.0 items (Box 5)
  - 1979, 2.0 items; Vallee, Bert L. (Box 5)
  - 1964, 1.0 item; Hulst, H. C. van de (Hendrik Christoffel), 1918- (Box 5)
  - 1962, 3.0 items; Vassy, E. (Box 5)
  - 1978, 2.0 items; Vedrenne, G. (Box 5)
  - 1972, 2.0 items; Venkatesan, D. (Doraswamy), 1924-
  - 1976, 3.0 items; Vermeesch, Th. M. (Box 5)
  - 1974, 2.0 items; Villard, O. G., Jr. (Box 5)
  - 1978, 2.0 items; Voisin, Mike (Box 5)
  - 1965-1973, 8.0 items; Ditfurth, Hoimar von (Box 5)
  - 1977, 2.0 items; Vucovic, Jovica (Box 5)
  - W - Misc., 1962-1999; 25.0 items (Box 5)
  - W. W. Norton & Co., 1991-1992; 5.0 items (Box 5)
  - 1978, 3.0 items; Wallhof, Hans (Box 5)
  - 1962, 6.0 items; Warga, Mary (Box 5)
  - 1961, 2.0 items; Warner, B. (Box 5)
  - Washington Academy of Science, 1954; 1.0 item (Box 5)
  - 1975, 2.0 items; Way, Mack (Box 5)
  - 1961-1962, 3.0 items; Wentzel, Donat G., 1934- (Box 5)
  - 1966-1967, 4.0 items; Weymann, R. J. (Ray J.) (Box 5)
  - 1965-1979, 4.0 items; White, Robert M. (Box 5)
  - Who's Who In America, 1963; 8.0 items (Box 5)
  - Wiesner, Jerome, 1961; 1.0 item; Wiesner, Jerome B. (Jerome Bert), 1915-1994 (Box 5)
  - Wilson, R., 1970; 3.0 items (Box 5)
  - 1964, 3.0 items; Winckler, John
  - 1967, 2.0 items; Wing, Albert (Box 5)
  - 1977, 4.0 items; Wolfe, Arthur M., 1939- (Box 5)
  - 1962-1963, 2.0 items; Wolfle, Dael Leev, 1906- (Box 5)
  - 1967, 5.0 items; Womack, E. A. (Box 5)
  - 1961, 3.0 items; Woodridge, David (Box 5)
  - Y - Misc., 1967-1988; 7.0 items (Box 5)
  - Zisman, William A., 1970-1972; 8.0 items (Box 5)
  - 1978, 2.0 items; Zombeck, Martin V. (Box 5)
- Series II. Research Materials and Notes, 0.5 linear feet
  Series II is comprised of Dr. Friedman’s research material from his time at the Navy Research Laboratory. It consists mainly of diagrams and charts of experiments, as well as some research notebooks.
  - Charts, Ion Production and Density, 1954; 2.0 items (Box 6)
  - Notes, A Diffusive Atmosphere, 1954; 7.0 items (Box 6)
  - Notes, D-Layer, Undated; 3.0 items (Box 6)
  - Notes, Gamma Ray Astronomy, Undated; 2.0 items (Box 6)
  - Gamma Ray Bursters, Notes, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Undated; 49.0 items (Box 6)
  - Notes, Oxygen Absorption In the Upper Atmosphere, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 6)
  - Notes, Oxygen in Ionosphere, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 6)
  - Notes, Procedure To Compute Density of Ionization, Undated; 5.0 items (Box 6)
  - Notes, Space Weather, 1995; 2.0 items (Box 6)
  - Notes, Temperature of the Corona, 2.0 items (Box 6)
  - X-Rays, Notes, Undated; 2.0 items (Box 6)
  - Yohkoh, Notes, 1.0 item (Box 6)
  - Notes, 3.0 items (Box 6)
  - Research Notebooks, Undated; 2.0 items (Box 6)
  - Voltage Chart, V-2 Rocket Test #49, 29 Sept. 1949, 1.0 item (Box 6)
- Series III. Works By Friedman, 1.5 linear feet
  Series III consists of manuscripts and printed copies of Dr. Friedman’s works. Included are articles for journals and magazines, as well as book manuscripts, including The Amazing Universe, The Sun and Earth and The Astronomer’s Universe.
  - Adrift in Space, 1966; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - "All of Us Who Knew Dr. Tousey...", Undated; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - Amazing Universe, Correspondence, 1975-1976; 51.0 items (Box 7)
  - An 80 Day X-Ray Light Curve of 3C 371, 1982; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - Applications of Electronic Methods to the Measurement of X-Ray and Gamma Ray Intensities, 1947; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - Applications of Geiger-Muller Counters to Inspection With X-Rays and Gamma Rays, 1942; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - Articles, Printed, 1949-1967; 19.0 items (Box 7)
  - Astronomer's Universe, Correspondence, 1989-1991; 34.0 items (Box 7)
  - Astronomer's Universe, Notes, 5.0 items (Box 7)
  - Astronomer's Universe, Reviews and Miscellaneous, 1990; 29.0 items (Box 7)
  - Astronomical Horizons at the Millenium, Notes, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - Astronomical Horizons, Correspondence, 1981; 12.0 items (Box 7)
  - Astronomical Horizons, Drafts, 1981, undated; 4.0 items (Box 7)
  - Astronomical Horizons at the Millennium, Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Astronomical Horizons at the Millennium, Draft, Undated; 3.0 items (Box 7)
  - Basic Theory and Fundamentals of Flourescent X-Ray Spectrographic Analysis, 1953; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - A Century of Space Science, Correspondence, 1999; 8.0 items (Box 7)
  - The Coincidence Pulse Discriminator, Undated; 8.0 items (Box 7)
  - The Collection of Long-Lived Natural Radioactive Products from the Atmosphere, 1952; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - The Contribution of Solar X-Rays to E-Layer Ionization, 1953; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - Copper and Nickel X-Ray KBZ- and KBG- Emissions Lines and K-Absorption Limits in Cu-Ni Alloys, 1940; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - Corona-Tube Regulators for High Voltages, 1949; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - Cosmic Life, 1980, undated; 2.0 items (Box 7)
  - Cosmic X-Ray Sources: A Progress Report, 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - Cosmic X-Rays and Gamma Rays, 1965; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - Cosmos Club Lecture, Feb. 21, 1991, 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - The Dawn of High Energy Astronomy, Publishing Agreement, 1961; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - The Dawn of High Energy Astronomy, Report of the Editor, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - The Dawn of High Energy Astronomy, Draft, Undated; 2.0 items (Box 7)
  - Detecting the Soviet Bomb: Joe-1 In a Rain Barrel, 1996; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - Detecting the Soviet Bomb, Correspondence, 1997; 2.0 items (Box 7)
  - Determination of Tetraethyllead in Gasoline by X-Ray Absorption, 1946; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - The Dissociation of Oxygen at High Altitudes, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - Dissociation of Oxygen in the Upper Atmosphere, 1955; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - The Dryden Lecture, 1973; 1.0 item (Box 7)
  - An Early Look at ATM Results, 1974; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Early Measurements of Solar Xrays, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Edward Olson Hulbert, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - The Effect of Chlorine and Bromine on the Work Function of Photon Counter Cathodes, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Exotic Astrophysics, 1974; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Five Year Outlook, Ch. 7, Sun and Earth, Draft, 1981; 2.0 items (Box 8)
  - Five Year Outlook, Ch. 7, Sun and Earth, Notes, Undated; 3.0 items (Box 8)
  - Flare Measurements from Rockets, 1957; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - The "Free Enterprise" Years, Undated; 2.0 items (Box 8)
  - From Ionosonde to Rocket Sonde, 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Geiger Counter Spectrometer for Industrial Research, 1945; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Geiger Counter Tubes, 1949; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - General History of Astronomy, 1983; 4.0 items (Box 8)
  - H0547-14: X-Ray Flux From A Weak Gamma-Ray Burst?, 1983; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - High Energy Astronomy, 1973; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - High Energy Astronomy, The NRL Role, 1978; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - High Energy Astronomy with HEAO, 1978; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - A High Temperature X-Ray Diffaction Apparatus, 1947; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - The Inconstant Sun, 1980; 3.0 items (Box 8)
    10 photographs from this folder have been moved to Series XI, Photographs.
  - "In a Panic to Counter the Soviet Success..." incomplete manuscript, Undated; 1.0 item
  - The IGBO and the ISY, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - IGY, IQSY and the Future of International Cooperation in Solar-Terrestrial Research, 1968; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - IGY and ISY, 1987; 2.0 items (Box 8)
  - The International Space Year, 1988; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - The Invisible Universe, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - An Invisible Universe Beckons, 1969; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - The Invisible Universe of X-Rays and Gamma Rays, 1997; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Ionospheric Constitution and Solar Control, 1964; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - The Ionospheric F2 Region, 1954; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Iosif Shklovsky and X-Ray Astronomy, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - The Legacy of the IGY, 1983; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Low Voltage Self-Quenching Geiger Counters, 1947; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Lyman - Alpha Radiation in the Solar Spectrum, 1953; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Measurement of High Intensities With the Geiger-Mueller Counter, 1946; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Milliroentgen Dosimetry With Thermoluminescence, 1957; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Near Earth Space, A Historical Perspective, Notes, Undated; 2.0 items (Box 8)
  - Near Earth Space, A Historical Perspective, Undated; 3.0 items (Box 8)
  - The New Revealing of the Sun, 1974; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - The Next 20 Years of Space Science, 1965; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Notes on X-Ray Astronomy, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Notes, Talk to the American Auto Society, 1956; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Occhialini Memoir, Correspondence, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Occhialini Memoir, Notes/Source Material, Undated; 2.0 items (Box 8)
  - Oda Biographical Note, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - The Optical Transmission of Additively Colored Alkali Halide Crystals in the Visible and Near Infra-Red, 1949; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Origins of Galactic X Ray Astronomy, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Overview, Solar Terrestrial Physics, Undated; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Particle Size Determination From X-Ray Line Broadening, 1946; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Perspectives on Space Science, 1976; 3.0 items (Box 8)
  - Photoelectric Measurements of Solar X-Rays and Ultraviolet, Undated; 1.0 items (Box 8)
  - Photon Counter Measurements of Solar X-Rays and Extreme Ultraviolet Light, 1951; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Photon Counters for the Far Ultraviolet, 1954; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Pulsars, 1970; 1.0 item (Box 8)
  - Q&A Notes, Undated; 3.0 items (Box 8)
  - Radioactivity of the Air, 1956 (Box 9)
  - Radiosensitivity of Alkali Halide Crystals, 1952 (Box 9)
  - Recent Progress and Future Prospects in High Energy Astronomy, 1972 (Box 9)
  - Remarks on Retirement, Undated (Box 9)
  - Remarks on the Occasion of the Sesquicentennial of the Naval Observatory, Undated (Box 9)
  - Richard Tousey 1908-1997, Notes and Research Materials, Undated (Box 9)
  - Richard Tousey 1908-1997, Correspondence, Undated (Box 9)
  - Richard Tousey 1908-1997, Undated (Box 9)
  - Rocket Astronomy - Window Into Space, Undated (Box 9)
  - Rontgenastronomie, Undated (Box 9)
  - The Science of Global Change - An Overview, Notes, Undated (Box 9)
  - The Science of Global Change - An Overview, Draft, Undated (Box 9)
  - The Science of Global Change - An Overview, Final Draft, Undated (Box 9)
  - Self-Quenching Halogen Filled Counters, 1947 (Box 9)
  - "Since the Launching of the First Artificial Earth Satellite...", Undated (Box 9)
  - The Soft X-Ray Background, 1973 (Box 9)
  - Solar Flares, 1969 (Box 9)
  - Solar Radiation in the Near Earth Environment, Draft, Undated (Box 9)
  - Solar Radiation in the Near Earth Environment, Images, Undated (Box 9)
  - The Solar Spectrum Below 2000 Angstroms, 1954 (Box 9)
  - Solar Terrestrial Energy Program: Major Scientific Problems, Historical Perspective, 1988 (Box 9)
  - Some Interdisciplinary Aspects of Sun-Earth Relationships in the Study of Global Change, Undated (Box 9)
  - Space Age Lessons About Our Environment, 1986 (Box 9)
  - The Space Age Universe, Undated (Box 9)
  - Space Science and the Frontiers of Physics, 1968 (Box 9)
  - Strip Chart Recording With An Autoscaler, 1950 (Box 9)
  - Sun and Earth, Correspondence, Undated (Box 9)
  - Sun and Earth, Publishing Agreement, Undated (Box 9)
  - Sun and Earth, Reviews, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Sun and Earth: A New View of Climate, 1979 (Box 9)
  - Thickness Measurement of Thin Coatings By X-Ray Absorption, 1946 (Box 9)